<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Epi | Academic</title>
    <link>/tag/epi/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/epi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Epi</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Epi</title>
      <link>/tag/epi/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive neuroscience</title>
      <link>/project/cogneuro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/cogneuro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this research line I used and sometimes still use mathematical modelling of cognitive processes, functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), and EEG to understand how humans make decisions, and how decision processes are different in adults with ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one paper, colleagues and I used the drift diffusion model of decision making and fMRI to describe how &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21118983/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;costs and benefits are represented in the brain&lt;/a&gt; during decision making. In a related paper we looked for &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20439711/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;representations of probabilistic evidence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also done &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20510376/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19822738/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt; on reinfocement learning in general, and how it is influenced by social learning, leading to the proposal that &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001089&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;following reward can in itself be rewarding&lt;/a&gt;. Some og this work has clear markers of a past time, like the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19822738/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;small-sample target-gene study&lt;/a&gt;. While this was exciting work at the time, I would approach this research differently today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently I have used quantitative models of decision making to understand decision making in ADHD. &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25477020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27608958/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; review describe the general idea. And here we use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27966103/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;drift diffusion model of decision making as a choice model for reinforcement learning&lt;/a&gt; in an attempt to described the effect of ADHD medication on decision making and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)</title>
      <link>/project/epi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/epi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this research line I use epidemiological approaches to learn more about rsik factors for ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One paper in this area examines &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31451995/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;how self selection into a study and loss to follow up can bias associations between exposures and outcomes&lt;/a&gt;, and how one can best reduce this bias. Elaborating on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15308962/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;seminal paper by Hernan and colleagues&lt;/a&gt; we point out that one cannot determine if large studies such as for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fhi.no/en/studies/moba/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bristol.ac.uk/alspac/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ALSPAC&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ukbiobank.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Biobank&lt;/a&gt; are generally &amp;ldquo;representative&amp;rdquo;. Instead the relationship between specific variables of interest in a study and variables that predict (continued) participation determine if bias is likely and how it should be accounted for. Importantly: When mental health related outcomes like ADHD, depression, etc. are involved, simply adjusting for participation predictors will often increase and not decrease bias. In comparison, inverse probability of participation weights will reduce bias. The reason for this is that participation predictors are often colliders between (mental health) outcomes and exposures, and conditioning on colliders introduces bias, but weighting does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other research colleagues and I investigate associations between maternal characteristics, often assessed in pregnancy, and developmental outcomes including ADHD. Differently then some research in this field we use Bayesian hierarchical regression models to estimate associations, which allows us to deal effectively with the multiple comparison problem, and we focus on effect sizes as opposed to statistical significance (using the MoBa, our sample size is often in the tens of thousands). So far our findings indicate that in rich industrialized countries the association between maternal nutrition or exposure to toxicants have &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31375821/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;such small effects and child developmental outcomes is small that it is unlikely practically meaningful&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
