<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Guido Biele</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ADHD risk factors</title>
      <link>/project/epi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/epi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this research line I use epidemiological approaches to learn more about rsik factors for ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One paper in this area examines &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31451995/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;how self selection into a study and loss to follow up can bias associations between exposures and outcomes&lt;/a&gt;, and how one can best reduce this bias. Elaborating on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15308962/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;seminal paper by Hernan and colleagues&lt;/a&gt; we point out that one cannot determine if large studies such as for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fhi.no/en/studies/moba/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bristol.ac.uk/alspac/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ALSPAC&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ukbiobank.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UK Biobank&lt;/a&gt; are generally &amp;ldquo;representative&amp;rdquo;. Instead the relationship between specific variables of interest in a study and variables that predict (continued) participation determine if bias is likely and how it should be accounted for. Importantly: When mental health related outcomes like ADHD, depression, etc. are involved, simply adjusting for participation predictors will often increase and not decrease bias. In comparison, inverse probability of participation weights will reduce bias. The reason for this is that participation predictors are often colliders between (mental health) outcomes and exposures, and conditioning on colliders introduces bias, but weighting does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other research colleagues and I investigate associations between maternal characteristics, often assessed in pregnancy, and developmental outcomes including ADHD. Differently then some research in this field we use Bayesian hierarchical regression models to estimate associations, which allows us to deal effectively with the multiple comparison problem, and we focus on effect sizes as opposed to statistical significance (using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fhi.no/en/studies/moba/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/a&gt;, our sample size is often in the tens of thousands). So far, our findings indicate that in rich industrialized countries the association between maternal nutrition or exposure to toxicants &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31375821/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;and child developmental outcomes are so small that they are unlikely to be practically sigfnificant.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian statistics</title>
      <link>/project/bayes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/bayes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Statistical inference is for me at the core of scientific activity because it allows us to learn in a systematic manner from data. Null hypothesis significance testing (NHST) is one one to learn from data, but it happens not to be my preferred way. This preference does not stem from some deep philosophical insight, but from the experience that forcing research questions into the NHST framework is not that helpful for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In research on decision making theoretical progress is, I think, more readily achieved by the formulation of quantitative models. When such models are reasonably complex, Bayesian estimation is often more reliably estimates model parameters than alternative approaches. Just as importantly Bayesian estimation as for example done in &lt;a href=&#34;https://mc-stan.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stan&lt;/a&gt; also signals when a model cannot be estimated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In epidemiological research, I think that effect sizes matter. Especially when one is dealing with large data sets in minor effect sizes can reach statistical significance. Using observational data will often require complex models that do the complexity of the data generating process justice. So even if Bayesian estimation of large epidemiological data sets can be much slower, I still prefer to wait for results I think I can trust more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I&amp;rsquo;ve published a few papers that uses Bayesian estimation. Click the &amp;ldquo;Bayesian&amp;rdquo; button below to see those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If time permits, I also answer the one of the other question on the the &lt;a href=&#34;https://discourse.mc-stan.org/u/guido_biele/summary&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stan user forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causal inference from observational data</title>
      <link>/project/causalinf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/causalinf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Randomised controlled trials (RCTs) are due to their internal validity considered as the gold standard for causal inference. But RCTs are not always feasible or ethical, for instance if one is interested in long-term effects of treatments. More generally, every investigation of causal effects trades off internal and external validity. Hence, one can argue that observational studies of causal effect, which tend to have higher external validity, have their place independent of the practical or ethical chellanges RCTs can pose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently establishing this research line after being rewarded a grant by the Norwegian Research Council. The thematic focus of this research is on the effect of medication and special education on educational and other outcomes of children with ADHD  .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One important challenge when estimating treatment effects is that of non-random selection into treatment or treatment by indication. To deal with bias from this and others we will use directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) to represent the (assumed) causal structure that generates the data we observe and to determine the best ways to deal with potential biases. Depending on the causal structure, adjustment, multilevel regression and post stratification, weighting or a combination of these approaches can be useful. We will also explore methods often used in econometrics like Difference in Differences or regression discontinuity, though it is uncertain that there is exist data in Norway to estimate such models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this research is to provide estimates of causal effects, even if we know that these are will always be imperfect. Our aim is to reduce this imperfection as much as we can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision making</title>
      <link>/project/dm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My research career started in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpib-berlin.mpg.de/research/concluded-areas/center-for-adaptive-behavior-and-cognition&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Centre for Adaptive Behavior and Cognition&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpib-berlin.mpg.de/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Max Planck Institute for Human Development&lt;/a&gt; in Berlin. This research line, in which I am currently not active, used experiments and mathematical modeling to understand decision making in a social context.
In one paper we investigated, using mathematical modeling of choices in public goods games, if cooperation in groups is better explained by simple &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2008-07158-002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reinforcement learning, or by reciprocity&lt;/a&gt;. In hindsight it is not surprising that reciprocity explained behavior better. At the time a number of researchers proposed reinforcement learning as models of cooperation, because they naturally explain how cooperation unravels in social dilemmas like the public goods game or the prisoners dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other papers in this area examined how basic reinforcement learning models can be modified to account for &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21585468/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;advice taking&lt;/a&gt; or for &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2009-07078-004&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pattern learning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this area fall also some papers that have mostly an interest in decision making in common, such as the one where we learned that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nowpublishers.com/article/Details/RBE-0034&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;economists did not use much rational analysis&lt;/a&gt; when deciding about taking a PSA test and that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0001691806000801&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;some ignorance can be better than imperfect knowledge&lt;/a&gt; when predicting outcomes of sports matches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision neuroscience</title>
      <link>/project/decneurosc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/decneurosc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this research line I used and sometimes still use mathematical modelling of decision making and learning, functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), and EEG to understand how human operant learning and decision making.We also investigate how learning and decision making processes are different in adults with ADHD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one paper, colleagues and I used a sequential sampling model of decision making and fMRI to describe how &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21118983/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;costs and benefits are represented in the brain&lt;/a&gt; during decision making. In a related paper we looked for &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20439711/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;representations of probabilistic evidence&lt;/a&gt; during reard bases decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also done &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20510376/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19822738/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt; on reinforcement learning in general, and how it is influenced by social learning, leading to the proposal that &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001089&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;following advice can in itself be rewarding&lt;/a&gt;. Some of this work has clear markers of a past time, like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19822738/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;small-sample target-gene study&lt;/a&gt;. This was exciting work at the time, but I would approach this research differently today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, I have used quantitative models of decision making to understand decision making in ADHD. We have published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25477020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;meta analysis&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27608958/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;theoretical review&lt;/a&gt; which describes how we can use quantitative models of decision making to better understand the development and symptoms of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder. In an empirical paper we use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27966103/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;drift diffusion model of decision making as a choice model for reinforcement learning&lt;/a&gt; to described the effect of ADHD medication on decision making and operant learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of medication and special education</title>
      <link>/project/nfrsea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/nfrsea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this amazing project we fuse cutting edge scientific technologies like causal data science, big data, and probabilistic machine learning to predict how to boost school-performance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is how one could describe this project if the goal is to describe the it with a bunch of flashy terms. What we are really trying to do is to answer an important but hard question, &amp;ldquo;Do ADHD medication and special education improve school performance?&amp;rdquo; as well as we can with observational data. In order to do this we will used structural models (&lt;em&gt;causal data science&lt;/em&gt;), lots of data from registries (&lt;em&gt;big data&lt;/em&gt;), and Bayesian estimation of structural models (&lt;em&gt;probabilistic machine learning&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most children with ADHD have minor or severe reading and writing problems already in the third grade. A substantial proportion of children and youth receive special educational assistance and/or ADHD medication. This begs the question: Do medication and special educational assistance improve school performance? This question is important because the few papers that looked at long-term effects of medication find only rather small effects, and we know even less about the long-term effects of special educational assistance.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-special-education-adhd-medication-and-early-reading-difficulties-in-norway-special-education-and-use-of-adhd-medication-increase-with-child-age-and-are-more-prevalent-among-boys-children-with-adhd-are-10-times-more-likely-to-have-severe-reading-difficulties-than-children-without-adhd-as-early-as-grade-3-data-from-httpsgsiudirno-httpwwwreseptregisteretno-norwegian-mother-and-child-cohort-study&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/project/nfrsea/SA_MHP_SE_hu710ed5685c68796413877da6d0e8d741_361632_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Special education, ADHD medication and early reading difficulties in Norway. Special education and use of ADHD medication increase with child age and are more prevalent among boys. Children with ADHD are 10 times more likely to have severe reading difficulties than children without ADHD as early as grade 3. Data from &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;https://gsi.udir.no&amp;#34;&amp;gt;https://gsi.udir.no&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#34;http://www.reseptregisteret.no&amp;#34;&amp;gt;http://www.reseptregisteret.no&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;, Norwegian Mother and Child Cohort Study.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/project/nfrsea/SA_MHP_SE_hu710ed5685c68796413877da6d0e8d741_361632_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;4819&#34; height=&#34;1134&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Special education, ADHD medication and early reading difficulties in Norway. Special education and use of ADHD medication increase with child age and are more prevalent among boys. Children with ADHD are 10 times more likely to have severe reading difficulties than children without ADHD as early as grade 3. Data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://gsi.udir.no&#34;&gt;https://gsi.udir.no&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reseptregisteret.no&#34;&gt;http://www.reseptregisteret.no&lt;/a&gt;, Norwegian Mother and Child Cohort Study.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some methods&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project we are using data from Norwegian registries and the Norwegian Mother, Father and Child Cohort Study (MoBa) to estimate the effect of medication and special education on school performance of children with ADHD or other mental health or developmental problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using observational data to estimate treatment effects is difficult (some would say impossible), because individuals are not randomized into treatment conditions. We are still doing this project for two reasons. First, we are interested in effects of longer-term treatments, but conducting randomized controlled trials (RCTs) is considered unethical if one wants to estimate long-term effects of treatments that one assumes should be beneficial. Secondly, well designed placebo controlled randomized trials have the strongest internal validity, if we see outcome differences between treatment conditions those are due to the treatment, but they still can have a sub-optimal external validity, i.e. we remain uncertain about how the treatment effects generalize to treatment that is not implemented as part of an RCT. Reasons for a limited external validity include less formalized implementation of treatments outside RCTs or non-random selection of participants into the RCTs. Therefore carefully implemented observational studies can be a useful complement to RCTs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach to a careful implementation of an observational study is to formulate a structural model that describes our assumed data-generating process, and to use Bayesian estimation of hierarchical models to obtain estimates of causal effects.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-directed-acyclic-graphs-dags-of-design-and-causal-assumptions-a-school-performance-at-time-t2-spsubt2sub-results-of-national-tests-in-grades-8-and-9-depends-on-medication-med-individual-special-education-ise-and-on-confounders-like-earlier-school-performance-spsubt1sub-national-tests-grade-5-parental-education-edu-and-comorbid-disorders-com-other-potential-confounders-like-gender-parityparental-mental-health-and-income-are-omitted-here-for-clarity-b-bias-from-observed-confounders-here-spsubt1sub-which-predicts-exposure-med-and-outcome-spsubt2sub-can-be-controlled-by-adjusting-for-them--c-when-spsubt1sub-is-a-collider-between-usubpasub-iunobservedi-parental-attention-and-usubscsub-iunobservedi-school-quality-adjustment-for-spsubt1sub-leads-to-conditioning-on-a-collider-and-cannot-correct-bias-adjusting-for-a-propensity-score-derived-from-spsubt1sub-also-introduces-bias-instead-inverse-probability-of-treatment-weights-need-to-be-used&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/project/nfrsea/SA_DAG_hu1fa7f68cd89c310b2967bed16dba5334_272042_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) of design and causal assumptions. (a) School performance at time t2 (SP&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;t2&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;, results of national tests in grades 8 and 9) depends on medication (MED), individual special education (ISE), and on confounders like earlier school performance (SP&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;t1&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;, national tests grade 5), parental education (EDU), and comorbid disorders (COM). Other potential confounders like gender, parity,parental mental health and income are omitted here for clarity. (b) Bias from observed confounders (here SP&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;t1&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;, which predicts exposure MED and outcome SP&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;t2&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt;) can be controlled by adjusting for them.  (c) When SP&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;t1&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; is a collider between U&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;PA&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; (&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;unobserved&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; parental attention) and U&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;SC&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; (&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;unobserved&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; school quality), adjustment for SP&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;t1&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; leads to conditioning on a collider and cannot correct bias. Adjusting for a propensity score derived from SP&amp;lt;sub&amp;gt;t1&amp;lt;/sub&amp;gt; also introduces bias. Instead, inverse probability of treatment weights need to be used.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/project/nfrsea/SA_DAG_hu1fa7f68cd89c310b2967bed16dba5334_272042_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;3437&#34; height=&#34;2218&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) of design and causal assumptions. (a) School performance at time t2 (SP&lt;sub&gt;t2&lt;/sub&gt;, results of national tests in grades 8 and 9) depends on medication (MED), individual special education (ISE), and on confounders like earlier school performance (SP&lt;sub&gt;t1&lt;/sub&gt;, national tests grade 5), parental education (EDU), and comorbid disorders (COM). Other potential confounders like gender, parity,parental mental health and income are omitted here for clarity. (b) Bias from observed confounders (here SP&lt;sub&gt;t1&lt;/sub&gt;, which predicts exposure MED and outcome SP&lt;sub&gt;t2&lt;/sub&gt;) can be controlled by adjusting for them.  (c) When SP&lt;sub&gt;t1&lt;/sub&gt; is a collider between U&lt;sub&gt;PA&lt;/sub&gt; (&lt;i&gt;unobserved&lt;/i&gt; parental attention) and U&lt;sub&gt;SC&lt;/sub&gt; (&lt;i&gt;unobserved&lt;/i&gt; school quality), adjustment for SP&lt;sub&gt;t1&lt;/sub&gt; leads to conditioning on a collider and cannot correct bias. Adjusting for a propensity score derived from SP&lt;sub&gt;t1&lt;/sub&gt; also introduces bias. Instead, inverse probability of treatment weights need to be used.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are starting with a base population of around 600,000 children that were born between 2000 and 2100. The study population consists of children with ADHD or other mental health or developmental problems (up to maybe 60,000), and these children&amp;rsquo;s parents and siblings. Parents and siblings are an important part of children&amp;rsquo;s environment, which has an influence on school performance generally, and which can also influence how effective treatments are implemented. Special education data is only available from MoBa, so that sample sizes will be smaller for these analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Age&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;6,7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;11-14&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;15&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Diagnoses&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ADHD symptoms&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Therapy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR, KUHR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR, KUHR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR, KUHR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR, KUHR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR, KUHR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR, KUHR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR, KUHR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Medication&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NorPD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NorPD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NorPD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NorPD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NorPD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NorPD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NorPD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Special education&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;School perform.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;MoBa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parental edu &amp;amp; income&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;SSB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Parental diagnoses&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;NPR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pilot analyses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To check the general feasibility of the project I did some pilot analyses on MoBa, NPR, and NorPD data (N ~ 1,500 children with ADHD). I used a hierarchical Bayesian ordered regressions to estimate the effect of special education in kindergarten or ADHD medication on reading problems in the 3rd grade. I used inverse probability of treatment weights to adjust for confounding by indication. The effect estimates are on average positive, but also vary substantially between subgroups characterised by maternal education and child gender.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-results-from-prelimiay-analysis-itop-lefti-effect-estimate-for-adhd-medication-itop-righti-effect-estimate-for-special-education--ibottom-lefti-bivariate-distribution-of-medication-years-and-dosage-for-10-12-year-old-children-darker-shading-indicates-more-frequent-combinations-ibottom-righti-more-hours-special-education-per-week-are-associated-with-fewer-reading-problems-averaged-across-groups-shaded-areas-show-25-95-credible-intervals&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/project/nfrsea/SA_prelim_hud6f8f92b120c35ec75c67835976c9346_343521_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Results from prelimiay analysis. &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Top left&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;: Effect estimate for ADHD medication. &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Top right&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;: Effect estimate for special education.  &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Bottom left&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;: Bivariate distribution of medication years and dosage for 10-12 year old children. Darker shading indicates more frequent combinations. &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;Bottom right&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;: More hours special education per week are associated with fewer reading problems (averaged across groups). Shaded areas show 25-95% credible intervals.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/project/nfrsea/SA_prelim_hud6f8f92b120c35ec75c67835976c9346_343521_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;2835&#34; height=&#34;2409&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Results from prelimiay analysis. &lt;i&gt;Top left&lt;/i&gt;: Effect estimate for ADHD medication. &lt;i&gt;Top right&lt;/i&gt;: Effect estimate for special education.  &lt;i&gt;Bottom left&lt;/i&gt;: Bivariate distribution of medication years and dosage for 10-12 year old children. Darker shading indicates more frequent combinations. &lt;i&gt;Bottom right&lt;/i&gt;: More hours special education per week are associated with fewer reading problems (averaged across groups). Shaded areas show 25-95% credible intervals.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Working packages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WP0 provides input for and guides working packages that implement the research and also organizes acquisition of register data and communication with users. WP1-WP3 follow a similar approach: Treatment patterns and predictors are identified in a first step, based on which effects are estimated in a second step. WP1 focuses on medication and uses data from Norway and Sweden. WP2 focuses on special education. WP3 focuses on interaction effects of special education and medication.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-working-packages-and-their-dependencies&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/project/nfrsea/workplan_hu5a560d501c31d91dffa8e99f712e2091_694900_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Working packages and their dependencies&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/project/nfrsea/workplan_hu5a560d501c31d91dffa8e99f712e2091_694900_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;4596&#34; height=&#34;2597&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Working packages and their dependencies
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Collaborators&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will be implemented in collaboration with colleagues in Norway, Sweden, and the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.med.uio.no/imb/english/people/aca/jonmic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jon Michael Gran&lt;/a&gt; (University of Oslo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fhi.no/en/about/departments-and-centres/child-health-and-development/mari-vaage-wang/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mari Vaage Wang&lt;/a&gt; (NIPH, Oslo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fhi.no/en/about/departments-and-centres/chronic-diseases-and-ageing/oystein-karlstad/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Øystein Karlstad&lt;/a&gt; (NIPH, Oslo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://samforsk.no/Sider/Ansatte/Christian-Wendelborg.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Christian Wendelborg&lt;/a&gt; (NTNU, Trondheim)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://staff.ki.se/people/henlar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Henrik Larsson&lt;/a&gt; (Karolinska Institiute, Stockholm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.northumbria.ac.uk/about-us/our-staff/c/reinie-cordier/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Reinie Cordier&lt;/a&gt; (Northumbria University, Newcastle)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mats Fredrirksen (&lt;a href=&#34;siv.no&#34;&gt;Sykehuset i Vestfold&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nina Holmen (&lt;a href=&#34;adhdnorge.no&#34;&gt;ADHD Norge&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
