<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DecMak | Academic</title>
    <link>/tag/decmak/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/decmak/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>DecMak</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>DecMak</title>
      <link>/tag/decmak/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decision making</title>
      <link>/project/dm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My research career started in the centre of Adaptive Decision Making and the Max Planck Institute for Human Development in Berlin. This research line, which I am (unfortunately) no longer active in used experiments and mathematical modeling to understand decision making in a social context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one paper we investigate, using mathematical modeling of choices in public goods games, if cooperation in groups is better explained by simple &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2008-07158-002&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reinforcement learning, or by reciprocity&lt;/a&gt;. In hindsight it is not surprising that reciprocity explained peoples behavior better. At the time a number of researchers proposed reinforcement learning as models to explain (the often unraveling) cooperation in groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other papers in area examined how basic reinforcement learning models can be modified to account for &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21585468/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;advice taking&lt;/a&gt; or for &lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2009-07078-004&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pattern learning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this are fall also some papers that have mostly an interest in decision making in common, such as the one where we learned that (economists did not use much rational analysis)[https://www.nowpublishers.com/article/Details/RBE-0034] when deciding about taking a PSA test and that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0001691806000801&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;some ignorance can be better than imperfect knowledge&lt;/a&gt; when predicting outcomes or sports matches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
